There was a time last year where most of
the engineers that I knew were starting
to use AI coding assistants. But I
refuse to be one of those people. And I
know that might come as a surprise to
you, especially if you've seen any of my
recent content. But I was one of those
people that thought that large language
models were great for helping you plan
your development. But why in the world
would you trust them for implementing
and validating? Now, obviously, my
understanding and my AI coding systems
have evolved since then, and I use AI
coding assistants to help me write all
of my code. But validation is also a
very important part of what I like to
call the PIV loop. This is my system for
using AI coding assistance that I've
covered a bit on YouTube and also I'm
covering a lot in the Dynamis Agentic
coding course. So, validation is all
about giving your coding assistant the
ability to check its own work after it
has finished an implementation. and
coding agents checking their own work is
super common. You'll see it all the
time. But I still think that validation
is the most undervalued aspect of any AI
coding workflow because most of the time
when you see this kind of thing, it's
just have the coding agent write a
couple of unit tests, do some linting,
maybe run the application, but there's
nothing that's really endto-end
validation. And so I took it upon myself
as a challenge recently to see how far I
can push AI validation. and I have
gotten some insane results. I basically
created a process for your coding agent
to create a living and breathing system
for validating your entire application
end to end. Basically replacing all
vigorous manual testing you might have
to do yourself and going through all the
different user flows. And I've applied
this to some pretty complex projects
with a lot of success. And it all boils
down to a single prompt that I'm sharing
with you in this video. So what we have
here is a meta command. You can run this
on any codebase with any AI coding
assistant. And so it'll do deep research
on your project, figure out how it can
validate things completely end to end,
and then it's called a meta command
because it creates another command
called validate.md. This is what you can
run going forward to kick off this full
end toend validation cycle. So I have a
link to this in the description. You can
go and try this out right now on any
project. And yeah, you might already
have a system for validation, but you'll
probably be blown away by what you can
do with this. It might seem
overengineered, but I've been so
impressed with this. And let me be
clear, running this yourself is as easy
as bringing the command into your
codebase and then for cloud code, you
can just do ultimate validate command.
Boom. No arguments or anything. You just
send this off and it's going to analyze
your codebase and create that
validate.md.
And then if you are using a coding
assistant that doesn't support slash
commands like cursor for example you can
just say go and read and then give it
the path to this command like rightclick
copy relative path and then execute
these instructions now right so commands
are just prompts it's okay if you don't
have slash commands in your AI coding
assistant you send this off you get your
validate and then you can just run
slashv validate once it's created
probably iterate on it and like validate
it yourself you want to you know
validate the validate command. But once
you're really confident with what you
got here, you can use this going forward
to like go through that entire process
and save you potentially dozens of
minutes every single time you build a
new feature. So it just makes your
development workflow, all your cycles
that much faster. And this entire thing
started when I was working on this
application. This is my remote coding
agent. And I've been pouring hours and
hours into building this. You can think
of it like cloud code for the web,
codeex or factory, like all those remote
coding agents, but it's entirely custom
system that I built and I built it in a
way where it's super extendable. You can
integrate with a ton of different
platforms like Telegram, GitHub. I'm
adding in Slack. You can pick your
coding assistant like Cloud Code or
Codeex. I'm adding in Open Code. It's
pretty cool. And I'm giving this all
away to you, by the way, but only in a
live stream that I'm doing on November
29th. So, check the description in the
pin comment. go enable notifications for
that stream. It's going to be a blast
and you're going to get all of this. And
I'll show you really quick like going
into GitHub, I can mention the agent and
through the GitHub web hook, it'll kick
off my coding assistant to handle this
entire issue for me and even open up a
pull request and I can inject my own
custom commands and process into this.
And I'll show you something kind of
similar in Telegram as well, just having
it summarize a read me on the current
GitHub repository that I have it
operating on. And this is entirely
remote. Like I can even do this from my
phone. It's super cool. But you can see
as I'm demoing this here that it's
pretty complicated. Like every time I
implement a new feature, I have to test
Telegram. I have to test GitHub. I have
to try the different coding assistants.
And so as I was going through this, it
was a bit overwhelming all of the
validation that I had to do. And so I
started thinking to myself like how
could I create a process for the coding
assistant to go through all these
different user flows and test these
different integrations so I don't have
to myself. And a skip and a hop later, I
ended up with this ultimate meta command
that I showed you earlier. And I'm just
kidding. It actually took a while to get
to this point. But I just started with
that problem. I have too much to
validate and I need the coding assistant
to help me. But I still need to have
confidence. That's why I needed to go
through all of the user flows. Basically
testing the app just like I would do if
I was testing it rigorously. And so even
using tools like the GitHub CLI to
actually create issues in pull requests
and tag the agent, go and read the pull
request comment after to make sure that
everything is aligned with the request.
Doing all of that completely end to end.
And man, it has been incredible seeing
it work. Even go for like 45 minutes
with the validate command that I have
for this that I'll show you in a little
bit. But it did take a while to get to
this point, especially this more generic
version that you can now use on any
codebase. But it started really simple.
Like I'll actually show you an example
of this right now. I'll create a new
command called pleasehel.m MD and I'll
show you kind of what it looked like at
first for me to just ask the coding
assistant to help me with this. So I
just started with I need help validating
my project. There are just so many
different edge cases and user flows to
test. So I want you to analyze the
codebase deeply to understand all the
different flows, edge cases, how the
application is structured, how we can
really validate things end to end. Now
this isn't exactly what I typed at
first, but it's pretty close. So I'm
giving you kind of a live recreation
here. And after you understand the
codebase and user flows, I want you to
think about how you can validate this
app end to end and what tools you would
use specifically. So for example, this
is a Docker application. We're using
GitHub. I want you to think about how
you could use the GitHub CLI. Think
about all the tools you can use to
validate things as a user would. And I
think this is like the key that really
unlocked this next level of validation
for me. It's just like telling it to act
as a user and use tools like the GitHub
CLI to do a lot more than just simple
unit testing with justest or piest for
example. And so like if I were to do
things end to end myself, how can you
mimic that? And when I say end to end, I
mean end to end do not hold back. Like
yeah, usually coding assistants
overengineer and I try to tell it to
keep it simple, but here I wanted it to
generate a massive validate document so
that we have this command that goes for
a really long time going through all
these edge cases. And then finally, I
want you to help me create a command
that does all the validation end to end.
I want it to be extremely comprehensive
and also include any of the other
testing we're already doing here, like
you know, the unit testing, the linting,
the type checking, like all of that. I
still want to include that, but most of
the prompt is going to be the end to end
testing. And so I I threw this into the
coding assistant and what it came back
with was pretty much what I accepted
right away. I did some iteration on the
the tooling and things like that, but
I'll show you the validate command that
I've been using on this project and I've
run this probably a dozen times now. It
is super super accurate. Like it's
actually so consistent every single
time. It goes through all of these
tests. So take a look at this. So first
of all, it does all of the higher level
testing like the type checking and
linting and unit testing all that. But
now it gets into this test repository
setup. It will literally create a new
GitHub repository for me so that I can
test my remote agents on top of it. So
it cleans things up. It creates the
GitHub repo and the web hook so I can
receive those mentions in GitHub and
then it will mimic some of the testing
for Telegram. And it even created its
own code like it injected API endpoints
to like mimic telegram functionality.
It's so cool. And so it does all that
after it does its docker testing. So
that's the test adapter. This is kind of
like the telegram simulation. Then after
it does that, it even does database
validation. So it checks to make sure
that my conversations are being stored
in my database. Very very cool. Then it
does the GitHub integration testing. So
it'll create an issue, mention the
agent. Like man, it it cannot get more
comprehensive than this. It makes sure
that the pull request is created and it
validates all that. It tests to make
sure that it can kick off different
coding agents in parallel. It says it's
optional. U but I have seen it do this
every single time and like works really
really well. Um and yeah, it also tests
all these custom commands that I have it
create for like priming and planning and
executing kind of like the piv loop that
I was talking about earlier. So, yeah, I
I don't need to like keep going through
all this right now, but yeah, you can
see how long this is, and it's still
super consistent because it's just a
super structured step-by-step process,
even with a really nice summary report
at the end. And I guess the AI coding
assistant is just trying to maximize my
dopamine here cuz I get all of these
green check marks at the end. I'm
actually showing you a previous
execution that I did of the full
validation workflow. And it's not that
long overall because it's mostly just a
ton of calls to Docker and the GitHub
CLI. So I can scroll all the way back up
to the top where it runs that highle
initial testing like linting and unit
testing. Then it creates the GitHub
repository and validates all of that. Um
and then it does everything in GitHub
even validating the database. And
sometimes it makes these mistakes but it
always corrects itself. And so yeah, the
validation is non-deterministic because
we're leaving it up to a coding
assistant, but like I said, it's caught
real bugs and it's just fascinating to
watch it rip through all of my user
flows and edge cases. It just gives me
so much confidence. Like the bugs that
it's found are things that I don't even
know if I would have found myself doing
manual testing. And so in some ways,
this is actually better than me
validating. And I think that there's
still room for me to test things myself.
And I wouldn't ship this to production
only trusting its validation. But me
plus the AI coding assistant is just way
better than only me, especially when the
testing is this comprehensive. But yeah,
looking at my private repos, you can see
that I've been testing the heck out of
this. And I've been getting really
consistent results. These are just some
of the repos. I've been cleaning up a
lot of them. But yeah, let me show you
how comprehensive this really gets. Like
if I click into one of these issues,
which by the way, all of these issues
and pull requests, the validate process
has created itself. I've made none of
these. So if I click into this one, like
add a footer section to the readme, just
a really simple issue because I want to
test things on a high level. I load in
the different commands that I have. So
I'm bringing in my own system. I get the
response which it's me every single time
but every other is actually the remote
coding agent and so then I invoke my
prime command so that it understands the
codebase and it reads the read me so
there we go it gets the project analysis
and then I ask it to or rather the
automation for the validation asks it to
plan the feature so it's invoking
commands so it's going through this
entire piv loop of priming then planning
then executing this entire process that
now I don't have to test myself and it
even goes back and checks these comments
comments to make sure that everything is
aligned and then it invokes this plan in
this feature branch that it also created
as a part of the automation. Like you
have no idea how much is truly going on
behind the scenes and then it creates
the pull request in the end here. So
there we go. Uh PR number 13. I can open
this up and I can see the final result
of my test here which it's also going to
go and validate this. Like this would
take like a solid 10 20 minutes to go
through this whole thing myself. But now
I can kick it off, go and eat my lunch
and come back and make sure everything's
looking good. And so the final thing I
want to say is please go and try this
command right now. Even if you already
have a solid system for validation for
your coding assistant, you might find
something new here. I mean, personally,
I've never had something as
comprehensive as this. And it blew my
mind what it was able to do and do
consistently with the process that came
out from this command. And like I said,
I've made it general now so that you can
use this on any codebase. So try it out.
Let me know in the comments how it goes
for you. And so with that, if you
appreciated this video and you're
looking forward to more things on AI
coding, more crazy fun stuff like this,
I would really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next